soft engineering radio episode 137 SQL
with jim mertens
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
I see radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every 10
days thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website possible
[Music]
hi everybody welcome to another episode
of software engineering radio this is
Arno and today I'm talking to Jim Melton
about the sequel programming language
Jim would you like to start by
introducing yourself cycle of words
about yourself yeah sure
I've been editor the SQL standard now
for well over two decades I think that's
a legal definition of crazy Wow
yes fact I've published every edition of
the standard except for the very first
one SQL 87 so it's kind of a life
sentence I think I'm also actively
involved at the w3c I am chairman of the
xml query working group there i've been
active and quite a few other standards
efforts over the years so basically i'm
just the standards professional living
if i had yeah that sounds like a very
special kind of career on the trend view
there anyway um what what would you say
to people like our listeners who who are
application developers who have sort of
sun exposure to databases but not our
natural database geeks what would you
say what is the sequel programming
language well SQL is a declarative
language it's a non procedural language
for defining what the results of queries
should look like and it does not specify
exactly how an SQL engine is supposed to
execute the query but it describes the
criterion for the query so the first
thing that most application programmers
have to get used to is the fact that it
is in fact non procedural but
declarative and that has enormous
advantages and a lot of different ways
the primary advantage is that it gives
the engine the freedom to optimize query
however it sees fit sometimes in ways
that would never occur to the average
program now it is I'm sorry go ahead so
the idea is not to to think about the
about performance about the execution
the first place but actually speak
expressive in a decorative way and leave
the performance tuning to the query
optimizer that's exactly right now it's
part of the fact that SQL is viewed as a
query language it does more than just
retrieve information it also can change
information in a database by adding new
information modifying existing
information or deleting information so
in that sense it's not a functional
language it definitely has side effects
but but is the Select sub language is
that a functional language very close to
the reason I would not say it's a
completely functional language is
because it is possible to invoke what we
call external function that is functions
that are written some other programming
language and once you escape to this
other programming language we have no
way of detecting what it is that that
little sub program is doing okay so a
lot of functional language was an escape
hatch correct why is it even a
programming language at first sight it
looks like it's just sort of four
statements you can push through the
twister database select insert update
delete why would even call it a
programming language it's so simple at
first sight I actually personally would
not call it a programming which what I
do is call it a query language or a data
sub line because it's meant to interact
with either programs written in another
language or directly with humans through
an interactive tool now there is an
aspect of SQL we call it at the standard
PSM or persistent storage modules that
does add a real programming capability
and in fact it's fairly procedural in
its nature
it has its analogue real-life products
such as oracle's pl/sql or microsoft's
transact-sql so store procedures are
actually have actually been standardized
yes they actually have been
unfortunately the only vendor of a major
database product that implements PSM the
way it's defined at the standard is IBM
the other major vendors already had
their own variations and they're
reluctant to support yet another syntax
for or semantics they've already
supported mmm-hmm how did SQL or sequel
get started what were the origins ah way
back when we're talking 1978 time right
oh wow yeah it's got its roots a long
time ago back when the nfl's were in the
caves I'm sorry I didn't understand BEC
Wendy in the end ourselves were in the
caves yeah yeah yes and I was one of
those Neanderthals yeah I got my
database start way before SQL back in
the network database days but in any
case
Ted God working for IBM develop the
relational model of data and IBM spent a
fair amount of effort and money
developing prototypes for a database
management system that implemented
something like the relational model
somewhere along there they begin
developing an actual query language to
operate this database engine a fellow
named Don Chamberlin and a friend of his
working at IBM developed this language
that they called at the time sequel seq
UEL and I believe that did stamp for
something like standard or our job sorry
structured English programming language
or something like that
Berkshire English query line
at some point in time we're now talking
and the early to mid 1988 a base group
was started under the auspices of ANSI
to develop a standard for database query
languages and the first thing they
worked on was a standard for network
database language codasyl databases if
you will but relational was becoming a
hot topic in the the academic community
and people began bringing in proposals
for another standard that they referred
to at the time as our QL our relational
query lang
that effort went on for two or three
years and it kept bogging down and
disagreements over the style of the line
until one day a fellow named Phil Shaw
who also worked for IBM brought in a
proposal for a language that he called
SQL and it was derived directly from
this work that Dante Merlin had done on
sequel and that was the start of the
standardization effort it took I believe
about a year or so before the first
version of SQL went out for public
review and by 1986
very late 1986 it was standardized in
the United States and in early 1987 it
was standardized what actually drove the
the standardization of the language who
was interested in actually standardizing
this I mean it's that wasn't the old
days when vendor lock-in was not
perceived as a bad thing so what got the
defenders to get together and actually
standardize this in such a good way it's
not clear exactly what the driving
factors were for most of the
organizations I know for some of the
vendors who eventually became the
dominant ones like Oracle IBM Sybase
driving motivation was the ability to
have the the illusion of portability so
that yes I'm being honest here so that
you could sell your system to a customer
and allow him to believe that there was
some chance he would be able to port his
programs that would not have been
walking so even though vendor lock-in
was not a big issue then it was on
people's minds nonetheless the other
factor though is that it allowed
incredible creativity in the engine
itself for example in the optimizer or
and how the storage system itself was
managed because unlike codasyl databases
the language was declarative and it gave
normos flexibility or optimizers to do
really dramatic improvement over what a
human programmer might be able to create
so before and the SQL standard asian
effort the query languages were not
armed strike we're not declarative but
procedural very much though our scene
which corresponds directly to the nature
of the database systems themselves for
example a codasyl database also known as
a network database was a highly
interconnected structure of Records and
one had to write an application program
in such a way that it would literally
pick up a link in one record that
pointed to another record and then it
would have to follow that link open the
new record put it into a different
buffer all of the logic was in the
application program itself yeah that
sounds pretty procedural and very
error-prone so how how comprehensive was
this first standardization effort what
was in this in the in it in the
beginning and how did it evolve later
well the first version of the standard
was I I think it's really fair to call
it a coiling it was very much a first
step
I would even say a baby step because it
provided only the basic four statements
that you've talked about and a
relatively small number of expressions
putting the usual arithmetic expressions
I don't believe that even had string
concatenation so is very restrictive
language but it got the doors open
actually developing a real Lang in SQL
eighty nine a minor revision of the
language was published that added what
one what we called at the time
referential integrity now this was only
restrictive referential integrity in
such a way that if you attempted to do
an operation such as delete a row that
would violate the referential integrity
you would get an error that's all there
was to it then you had to figure out how
to correct that problem in your
application mm-hmm by that mess qo
eighty-nine was published work had
already begun on the next generation of
the language which eventually was
published as SQL 92 although it was
called SQL two during us development
that was the first version of the
language in which entire applications
could be built by using only the
facilities in standard SQL for example
in SQL 86 and 89 there were no dated
data how to say this there were data
definition statements like create table
but there were no data structure
manipulation statements like alter table
to add a new column or to drop a column
so in SQL 92 we added all of those
additional statements for maintaining
the structure of the database as well as
for maintaining the content of the
database we also vastly increase the
different kinds of expressions built-in
functions new operators etc so it really
was a very pow
awful language by the time SQL 92 was
published then we started work on what
went by the name of SQL 3 for a while it
was eventually published seven years
later as SQL 1999 this is the period
during which we develop so-called
object-oriented SQL and what's that we
spent vast numbers of hours vast numbers
of months arguing about the object model
that an SQL database system should
support the idea was that we wanted
tables and databases to be used as
object repositories and in fact there
another group was formed called odmg the
object database management group and
they participated along with the SQL
people for a while to help us develop an
object model that would satisfy their
requirements and then they would use a
subset of SQL as a query language for
objects within each of their languages
so we did eventually develop an object
model that allows us to store rows and
tables that are two-sided Cohen on the
one side of the coin they're just
ordinary rows and ordinary tables but
you flip the coin over and on the other
side it looks like an object stored in
an object repository complete with
object references and all the usual kind
of things you would expect in an object
repository what's the difference between
a foreign key and an object reference
what do you mean by having object
semantics in the database ah well that
was part of what we argued about so for
so very long the way it ended up in SQL
1999 there is very little difference the
only difference that I think I'm sorry
the only two differences that I think
are really relevant are one we added
something called structured types which
allows you to store even in a column of
the database a very complex
they destructor mm-hmm but if you apply
that complex data structure the
structured tight as a row of a table you
now really do have a perfectly ordinary
table with perfectly ordinary rows in it
each attribute if you want to call it
that of the object that is stored there
or each field of the structure type
looks like an attribute of an object and
it has methods on it methods for
retrieving the value methods for
changing the value and you can write
arbitrary numbers of user-defined
methods so it really does begin to feel
like object the other difference though
is that we did not depend on referential
integrity per se for referencing these
object the reason for that is because
referential integrity is a is purely a
value-based concept in an SQL
environment
so the value that is stored in one
column of one table must be equal to the
value of some column some other table
whereas with object references we did
not want to have to depend on this value
base we wanted to have something a
little more abstract so we created
something called a reference type and
the reference type is oh it's
implementation to find what the contents
are but it is an post implementation
something like a row ID which is you
know just an abstract thing that your
database system produces it could even
be literally a disk address or it could
be the number of the row and some
sequential ordering of the rows in a
table the standard doesn't say what it
has to be but the big value of the
object references or of the reference
type is that you can't bring them into
your application program and send them
back into the database system so so they
have some sort of a non value usage even
in the application Pro
okay I see how'd it go on after that
well I believe that the object-oriented
CL stuff was not a very big success no
vendor that I know of has implemented
all of it
Oracle has implemented part of it Sybase
implemented part of at IBM implemented
part of it and the parts all overlap but
the the overlapping subset the the
intersection of all of those subsets is
not big enough I think build meaningful
applications consequently we didn't get
the uptake in customer usage that we had
hoped for and it was extremely expensive
to develop so so we learned a lot of
lessons while we were doing that and we
are not ever again going to do anything
that substantial I hope mm-hmm
after a skill 1999 was published we
began working on a version that
eventually was published as SQL 2003 SQL
2003 was I think you could properly call
it a maintenance version of the standard
it fixed a tremendous number of bugs and
it added only a small number of new
features we just recently published in
fact this year in fact SQL 2008 which
was more than just a maintenance version
we added a number of new features but
nothing nearly as notable as
object-oriented of SQL and we are
currently working on the subsequent
version of the standard which we hope
will be called SQL 2011 but it's
possible it could slip into 2012 mm-hmm
the truth is that a lot of people
consider SQL to be done that right now
what we're doing is adding features that
are more of interest to specific vendors
or maybe two or three vendors to one or
two vertical marketplaces but that don't
have the same broad
attraction that SQL did at the beginning
mm-hmm so the core is pretty stable and
there's things being added that are well
the more that's added to sort of the the
end of a of a curve that's being it
might go on forever but is less and less
interesting to the majority of people
yeah I think that's an accurate way of
putting it if you view a normal bell
curve we're pretty far out on one of the
tails probably at least one or two
standard deviations out okay but let's
take a look at the core of sequel I
expect that most listeners are familiar
with select star from table person or
something like that right how do you do
you go from there what's what kind of
expressions what kind of features does
SQL provide good ah oh it's kind of hard
to sum it up well just starting starting
somewhere but I'll try uh probably the
first thing that an application
programmer will encounter a need for is
to combine information from two or more
tables and the way one does this is
typically through an operation that we
call join and SQL provides a number of
different kinds of join but in general
the process is that you take rows in one
table and match them based on the
contents of certain columns let you
specify who rows another table and you
create a new virtual table that has the
number of columns that's equal to the
number of columns and the first table
plus the number of columns at the second
table and you start off with a number of
rows that's the product of the number of
rows in the first table the second table
I call that a cross-product but then you
filter that according to the joint
criteria so if the joint criteria says
that the employee ID and this table has
to be equal to the employee ID at that
table
you can throw away all of that cross
product in which that equality is not
true and now you're left with a a small
much smaller much more usable subset of
this cross product of rows in the two
tables after that you can apply further
filtering with the ordinary wear clause
and SQL that allows you to specify
arbitrary predicates to select only
those rows that are meaningful for
example you might choose to retain only
those rows for which the salary is less
than a hundred thousand euros mm-hmm
once you have gone that far the last
operation is actually what we call the
Select twist the syntax of SQL it is the
Select star or select a list of column
names so this very wide virtual table
that has all the columns from the first
table joined with all the columns in the
second table now project that virtual
table on to a specified number of other
columns and you now have a narrower
table that has only the column that have
the semantics requested what's the
difference between inner join and an
outer join an inner join is pretty much
what I've just described where you
retain only those rows from the first
table and the second table where there's
a match on the join condition an outer
join allows you to say but I also want
to keep all of the rows in the first
table that don't have any matches at all
at the second table an example of that
might be I would like to know about all
of my employees and the projects they're
assigned to
but even if I have employees that don't
have any projects on their plate right
now I want to know about them as well so
in that case you would do it outer join
and if you were saying let's join
employees with projects you do a left
outer join because you want to retain
all of the employees that don't have
projects if you wanted information about
the projects that don't have employees
assigned to them you would do a right
outer join instead and if you want
information about both those employees
that don't have projects on their plates
as well as projects that have no
employees assigned to them you can do
what's called a full outer join now one
has to ask what about all of those
columns in the virtual table that
correspond to the rows from the other
table the one in which there are no
matches well the values of those virtual
columns are just set to the SQL null
value
what about null what's the meaning of
null in SQL I was hoping you had asked
that nulls have turned out to be both
one of the most useful features of SQL
that most of the languages don't have
and also one of the most controversial
the meaning of a null value is precisely
what your application wants it to me
yeah I know I'm deliberately being vague
but I think the way I always explain it
to people is that the null value means
there is no value here it is a
placeholder for location where you could
store a value if you want to do but
there's not one there's not one there
right now now you could say it means
that the information is unknown or the
information is missing or the
information is not applicable in fact an
ANSI group a number of years ago wrote a
paper that came up with I think this is
the the right value 29 possible meanings
for the null value but still null does
not equal now absolutely because you
could substitute any other value for a
null and therefore in advance you can't
tell whether two nulls will have the
same value or have different values so
it's not equal it's also not
not equal so you so you have some kind
of tri-state logic absolutely and the
third the third state is unknown this
sounds pretty weird could sort of give
examples of that
well we build logic tables of course so
let me just sketch out an example of of
how the and operation would work if I
say that I have one predicate whose
truth value is false and another
predicate whose truth value is true
let's call them X and Y the result of x
and y has got to be false because a
false ended with a true is also false
it's only a true ANDed with the true
that can be true that's ordinary boolean
logic everybody understands that but
what if one of those truths values had
the value unknown instead of true or
false
what is the result of anding a true
value with an unknown value we don't
know the answer could be true or false
so in the logic tables that we build in
the standard we say that the result of
true and unknown is unknown but false
and unknown is always going to be false
so the answer there is gonna be false
it's not know so if I compare two
columns let's say the name column in the
person and the project name column in
the project and both are null then this
comparison will not be true although
they are from a perspective of normal
programming languages procedural
languages they would be the same but in
SQL it's unknown that is correct why was
that done well this is why it was very
controversial and remains controversial
to this day because eventually it is
possible that the
programmer name could be substituted
with a real name
Arno Haas and it is possible that the
project lead name could be substituted
could actually get a real name assigned
to it possibly Jim Melton now once those
two assignments had been made the
results of the comparison is gonna be
false but if the project lead name were
said to be Arno Haas then the result of
the comparison would be equal so until
we have actual values we don't know
whether the results is gonna be true or
false and it is misleading to pretend
that we do know so because the first
name the name of the employee is not
known and the name of the project lead
is not now then of course the result of
comparison comparing the two is not now
okay so now we have this tri-state logic
we have joins what else is there well
one of the earliest things that we
discovered was extremely valuable is
something that we call a sub query some
people call that an inner select a sub
query is a small query like another
select statement if you will that's
embedded inside an outer query now if
you really get down to the relational
algebra the Russian algebra is a way of
it of defining and expressing the
semantics of the relational model if you
really analyze the relational algebra
associated with sub queries you discover
that they're nothing more than a
different syntax for expressing joins
but sometimes expressing this
relationship as a sub query is much more
valuable a much more intuitive than
expressing it in the form of a joy
here's an example we want projects and
for all of our projects we want to have
we want to select only those projects
for which the sum of the employees
salaries is more than a million year
now now I can certainly express this by
doing a join between projects and
employees and computing the the sum of
the employees and filtering it out
inside a where cause and so forth but
sometimes it's more natural to say
select a project ID from Project where
then you can say open parentheses select
this the sum of the salaries of
employees assigned to that project is
greater than a million and express that
as another select inside the where
clause of the outer Select you can also
use these sub queries and the Select
twist itself so there's a it's it's
pretty much composable maybe not fully
composable in the sense that a lot of
functional languages are defined but
it's pretty composable so that the sub
select sub queries can be included in a
number of different places in the syntax
of the outer query okay um you know to
you mentioned some kind of several times
there's lots of functions in SQL what
about that ah there are quite a number
of built-in functions in SQL some of
them are trivial for example we have a
function called current time it takes no
arguments and it returns whatever the
system believes the current time is we
have other functions that do take
arguments like sub strengths for example
substring takes one string a starting
position and optionally a length of the
substring to extract we have functions
that implement regular expressions
cymatics so you can do regular
expression matching you can also do
regular expression extraction and
substitution
we have mathematical functions we have
what we might call statistical functions
and in fact and the SQL 2003 time frame
we added a large number of functions to
do
OLAP processing online analytical
processing so there's quite a few
functions for that
how well are these functions
standardized between vendors actually
very well the great majority of the
built-in functions are implemented by
the vendors using the precise semantics
that's in the standard a number of the
vendors have chosen not to use the exact
syntax for some of the early functions
because we define those functions using
sort of a keyword approach rather than
comma separated arguments for example
the substring function has substring the
first argument is the string from which
you're going to extract the substring
but instead of a comma following that we
have the keyword from and then the
second argument is the starting position
within that first string where you want
the substring to be extracted but
instead of following that with another
comma we have the keyword for and the
third argument if you provide it is the
length the number of characters are
number of bits that you want to extract
from the substring so some of the
vendors really didn't like this keyword
approach and they've just used ordinary
functional notation with commas
separating the arguments except for that
though the the vendors really have
picked up the correct semantics and in
many of the cases where the standard
chose to use the comma separated cement
syntax rather than the keyword syntax
the vendors have implemented exactly as
specified at the standard okay you
started out by saying that since SQL is
a declarative language programmers
should not worry about the
performance and just be as expressive as
possible and leave the optimization to
the query engine let's take a look at
what's going on there um what kind of
optimizations does a query optimizer
actually do ah here's a very trivial one
if we want to do a join where we say
we're matching employees with
departments the naive way of actually
executing such a join would be to
linearly go through the employees table
and every row you would then linearly go
through the project's table looking for
projects that at whatever criteria you
set up relative to that one employee row
now that's an extremely naive and
inefficient way of executing the joins
so instead you'll find that real
relational engines will probably have
built indexes that allow them to locate
rows in the employees table or locate
rows in the projects table that are
directly related to the criteria of the
join so instead of doing you know a
scrolling join or whatever you want to
call it the matches are done vastly more
effectively by going and finding the
exact rows that you're looking for based
on criteria now of course if you don't
have the capability of searching and
index for a particular kind of match you
might have to resort to scrolling
through an entire table but I found that
a lot of the optimizers will actually
build a quick index on the side because
they suspect that it's gonna be used a
number of times in this query so they'll
build a temporary index and use it for
the duration of the Quarian that perhaps
release it so clearly optimizer might
actually build an index that is not
explicitly declared by the application I
yes that is correct
kind of surprising to hear but is
optimizers that do that okay what what
else might a query optimizer do apart
from using indexes as with any
programming language optimizers have a
lot of different strategies a very
another very trivial one that an SQL
optimizer might do is inlining functions
so it would go essentially grab the code
associated with a function that's
written either in SQL or built into the
language and put the code in line rather
than have have to go through the context
switching or calling a subroutine it
also might do common expression
extraction and that's especially
valuable if you have sub queries if you
have a very very similar or even
identical sub query and multiple parts
of your query using a common expression
extraction you can do tremendous
improvements in the performance rather
than doing the naive approach of
actually invoking sub queries multiple
different times in different places and
coming up with essentially the same
results every time so so there's a huge
variety of things I have to say that I
believe the people who build SQ o engine
optimizers have got to be among the
smartest people on the planet well some
of the stuff they come with is just
incredibly creative stuff I would never
think of so the idea is basically to
actually really trust those smart guys
rather than try to be smarter than them
well that's the idea it doesn't always
work though customers are incredibly I
should say users are incredibly creative
when it comes to writing queries and
they're constantly coming up with
queries that the guys who are writing
the optimizers ever even imagined what
happened and therefore the optimizer
either just doesn't recognize the
structure of the query and doesn't do
anything smart with it or it might
actually misinterpret the query and do
something
bad with it as a result of this
potential problem
almost all the implementations have the
ability to show the application
programmer or to show the database
administrator what's called a query plan
it says well we broke the query down in
this way so we do a joint here we do an
equality match here we do a union here
you know we do all these operations in
this order well a really smart query
author might look at that go boy that's
gonna be really efficient really
inefficient for the kind of query I'm
really executing here let me see if I
can rephrase the query in an in a
different way that will allow the
optimizer to understand what I'm trying
to do one possible example there would
be maybe I'll do the join explicitly
rather than do a sub query and have the
depend hope that the optimizer
recognizes that it's supposed to be
doing a particular kind of join oh yeah
I see uh-huh so sort of try round them
and then always get the feedback where
the query optimizer actually does with a
query precisely and if you don't like if
you don't like it you might be able to
restructure the query most of the time
you end up calling your support people
and telling them your query optimizer is
not working so in the next version of
your product I hope you fix this okay
let's take a look at the data types that
SQL supports um what what's the range of
data types that's present well I don't
think anybody's going to be surprised at
it we have several different numeric
types we have integers and they come in
at least three flavors they're small int
integer and big yet the only requirement
is that big yet have a precision that's
not smaller than the precision of
integer and small and have a precision
that's not greater than the precision of
a nurture sort of sort of like see
actually there's no guarantee at all
that's correct there's no guarantee that
a big
we'll have more precision than a small
or no guarantee it s to the minimum
precision at all that's correct
this is the kind of thing that we expect
that the marketplace would sort out
because nobody's gonna buy a product for
a small man has two bits of precision
big yet has five bits of precision
mm-hmm now as it happens Oracle for
example the precision of big ant
small ant is identical and that's it's I
believe thirty nine digits decimal
digits so the precision is very big you
you don't get any benefits by saying
small ant over saying big within an
Oracle implementation but but isn't that
sort of wasteful we've got your space
not really that this is a place where
the engine people have gotten extremely
intelligent so for example Oracle does
not actually have fixed length columns
of 39 digits it's a variable length
column inside the row and so rows might
expand or shrink as you change the value
that's stored in the column wow that
sounds really smart and really hard to
come up with uh it actually wasn't that
hard to come up with consider the
problem of a character string column the
SQL standard defines two kinds of
character strengths uh there's fixed
length character strengths and there's
variable length character strikes
well once we had variable length
character strengths you don't want to
always allocate let's say 64 K bytes for
the maximum possible variable length
character strength
so instead virtually all the vendors
either have variable length columns or
they store the character string external
to the row and just have a link to it so
they might have a heap where they're
storing here the actual character
strength values itself and linked to the
heap from the from from the row itself
but doesn't I mean for for Strings
I see where that's useful but for
numbers doesn't that add significant
overhead rather than
having them in the row it is another
interaction for any number I don't
believe that Oracle stores the numbers
external to the row I believe it's
always in the row it's just a variable
length so rows are sort of variable
lengths indeed going on with the kinds
of data types that we have in addition
to the numeric types that I've mentioned
we also have there's actually three
kinds of character strengths we have
regular character string fixed length
variable length and we also have clubs
character large objects we have a byte
data type called binary where you can
store bite strength and they come in
fixed link variable length and Bob's a
binary large objects there are date/time
types there are interval types that to
express the difference between to date
times there's a boolean type that allows
you to express true/false or guess what
I know and then of course there's
user-defined types and user-defined
types come in two flavors one is
structured types that I mentioned
earlier where you can have arbitrary
structured complex structures of data
defined to be stored in a single column
of the database we also have something
we call distinct types so one might
define for example a type called IQ that
is a distinct type based on integer well
it's not very meaningful to add to IQs
together trust me
the IQ of a project is not the sum of
the I Tunes it's not even the average so
the point of a distinct type is that you
do not inherit the operations of the
parent type you have to define your own
operations so you define methods on the
distinct type so you would define a
method on IQ that perhaps allows you to
compare to I cute
but not to add the IQs together mm-hmm
coming back to the to the string types
why is there a distinction between the
variable length characters and AC lobe
they're both variable length why do I
have two different types that that was
also a controversial discussion we're
and we really debated it very seriously
for a long time before accepting the
Silom the reason boiled down to giving
hints to the engine it was felt that
most implementations would adopt a
maximum length for varying length
character strings that was let's say
reasonable enough that you would
actually store it inside the row like
possibly a maximum limit of one came
characters or one K bytes even does the
standard specifying the maximum length
or the minimum maximum length absolutely
not
the maximum length is implementation
defined so I know of one implementation
where the maximum length of a very of a
variable length character string is four
gigabytes Wow
I know of another implementation where
the maximum length is 200 bytes
oh so they vary tremendously now the
idea of accepting the c lob is to give a
hint to the engine that this could get
very very large and therefore you
probably want to store this external to
the row and just link to it so once
again I know implementations where the
maximum size of a Silom is 4 Giga
characters 4 billion characters and I
know others were it's the square of 4
billion characters Wow
yeah but that would fill up my hard disk
how big is the the performance impact
typically of using a C lob over using a
variable length character I think that
in real implementations the performance
hit is actually
modest one does end up doing something
like a joint but because the link is
very direct it sometimes mean it's only
one additional fetch out of the database
and a good optimizer will actually do
prefetches because as it's processing
the rows it knows that there's the
potential for the Bob or C lob column to
be addressed and so it can initiate a
prefetch to make sure that at least the
first chunk of the C lob is already
available so I think the performance hit
in general is pretty minor what would
you suggest we have any suggestions for
for developers sort of best practices
some advice for people who are not
seriously experts in SQL but write
database applications how to go about it
what would your advice be ah that's
actually very hard for me to say because
it's been so many years since I actually
developed applications right now I write
applications in XSLT for example rather
than SQL or C or anything else I think
the best practices are gonna vary widely
based on the kind of application for
example if one is doing an application
that requires a lot of strength
processing you're gonna have a totally
different approach to writing your SQL
statements than if you're doing
financial application and just to be
honest I'm just not competent to give
advice on best practices or SQL coding
and gentleman the one thing that I would
suggest is that authorization is
probably more important in SQL than it
is and in most other programming what do
you mean by modularization think about
your query various queries in terms of
the different components of it instead
of just saying well I've got four tables
that I need to correlate
and immediately doing a four-way join
think really carefully about whether
it's better to express one of those
joins in terms of a sub-query also you
might think in terms of how many rows
you actually think are gonna participate
in the joint from the first table the
second table the third table and so
forth and find out how your optimizer
treats a joint in terms of precedence it
gives based on left-to-right expression
of the join or right-to-left expression
of the joint and put the tables with the
smallest cardinalities and the position
at the join that is accessed first
therefore you are giving the optimizer a
lot of hints where it can do a much
better job of organizing your queries to
minimize disk accesses so there's
there's a lot of little hints like this
that you can get out of your
implementations documentation that is
extremely difficult to general but
that's the kind of a modularity that I
that I have in mind oh I see okay it's
also a good idea whenever possible to
use stored procedures or something very
close to stored procedures whereby your
queries are prepared well in advance
they're fully optimized and all you do
is invoke them it's a little bit like
calling a compiled subroutine the
contrary view point of that is what we
call dynamic SQL where you submit the
query in real time for it to be compiled
and optimized and then executed that's
massively inefficient you should do that
only if you're interacting with a human
being at Adam at a tool of some sort and
you don't know what kind of queries the
human is going to cause you to execute
but isn't there some sort of level
in-between at the driver level that the
drivers sort of pre compile the queries
or make sure the database pre-compiled
the queries and have a query cache of
the typically executed queries
even without having them in store
procedures absolutely most
implementations or at least most
commercial implementations do something
like that they do cache queries they may
even cache the results of relatively
small if the results are relatively
small the problem is that's an
implementation define capability it
can't be part of the standard and you
can't necessarily depend on your
implementation doing that or doing a
good job of it some implementations for
example might only cache who doesn't
where and when you come to the 25th one
it even throws away the first one or all
the 25th 26th etc all have to be treated
treated just as though they were
ordinary dynamic SQL so thinking about
it yourself and trying to trying to make
sure that you organize your queries in a
reasonable way and making stored queries
where it's going to be of general use
possibly to several different
application programs is a very smart way
of making sure that your performance
potential is maximum you're using the
term stored queries we're not saying
stored procedures and this is since it's
so controversial I'll be specifically is
talking about storing basically a single
select statement in the database and
call that are you talking about or is
your advice to actually put the logic in
to store procedures yeah I was a bit
casual with my language it would
actually be in a stored procedure or a
stored function we don't have the
capability of storing just a naked query
the database in the SQL stamp it it has
to be wrapped inside a stored procedure
or stored function but is your advice to
actually put a single select statement
into a storage function stored procedure
or will you was the advice to move to
massively move application logic into
store procedures and stored functions
just to be clear about what your advice
actually was the specific advice that I
was giving at that moment was to put an
individual query into a procedure a
stored procedure or stored but she
raised a very interesting point and that
is moving more of your application logic
into a stored procedure now there's a
lot of controversy about this different
people have radically different
viewpoints my viewpoint is the fewer
context switches you have the greater
potential you have or increasing
optimization not only do you forego the
actual CPU cost associated with changing
processes or contexts in some other way
but by putting all of your application
logic or more of your application logic
into a single language you now have the
opportunity to have an optimizer that
can optimize not only the query portion
of your applications but the logic
portion of your applications all at the
same time typically your application has
some kind of user interface you so
you'll have the context switches anyway
yes of course but but there are huge
portions of large applications that
don't involve user interface large
amounts of computations I've seen
applications that were hundreds of pages
of C code that have XS Q L select
exactly SQL select what we call embedded
SQL statements and every time you do an
exec ul you now have to do a context
switch between the C portion of the
application and the database portion of
the application the database engine and
its optimizer can only see the SQL
statement and it doesn't understand
can't even see the the C code so it
there's no possibility of doing
optimization that crosses query
boundaries
mmm-hmm whereas if you were to rewrite
that portion of your application and say
SQL PSM your optimizer now gets the
bigger picture it can say not only aah
he's trying to do a loop here I know how
to do loops in a smarter way by
extracting sub expressions he can also
say AHA this query and that query have a
lot of similarity to them so I will
create a query that is exactly the
intersection between the two sub queries
compile it
cache it away one time and then we'll
only do the the differences between the
two queries as a special case and the
two different places where they're both
what is your take on object relational
mapping tools oh I think they've gotten
a whole lot better in the last few years
they started off as a good idea but not
ready for primetime but in the last few
years I've seen some really good tools
no I can't give you any names because I
don't play with these things very much
mm-hmm but I've seen some really nice
tools that new object relational mapping
and quite intelligent ways unfortunately
most of them do not take advantage of
the object-oriented xql facilities they
just map them directly into ordinary
tables sometimes they do take advantage
of the structured types in SQL but not
all vendors implement that so you're
kind of narrowing the reign of
implementations to which that's
applicable okay thank you very much is
there anything you'd like to to sort of
wrap this this interview up with well
one of the things that I always have to
do is plea for more people to
participate the biggest problem we have
in the SQL standards development area is
that we are down to a very small core of
people from avert from really the major
vendors the five or six biggest vendors
um to develop the language and sometimes
we're not really certain whether our
ideas are the ones that are generally
applicable we would like more
participation not only from vendors but
or especially from actual users of the
line and even if people cannot
participate by attending meetings they
can always review the documents when
they're published for ballot in their in
their own country and submit comments to
tell us whether they like what we're
doing or whether they found bugs so more
participation is a good thing
so comments are actually welcomed and
well regarded and actually yeah if one
of the listeners actually wants to
participate he's welcome to share his
opinions absolutely we welcome it if the
comments are really sufficiently good
I'll travel over by the guy a beer cool
okay well thank you very much for taking
the time for the interview and thanks
for sharing your insights about the SQL
programming language my pleasure are now
thanks for inviting by
thanks for downloading and listening to
software engineering radio software
engineering radio is an educational
program brought to you by hillside
Europe if you want more information
about the podcast and all the other
episodes visit our website at se - radio
dot length if you want to support us you
can donate to the AC radio team via the
website or you can advertise press your
radio for example by clicking on the
Digg reddit delicious and slash dog
buttons to contact the team please send
email to team at SC - radio net or if it
is specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under
creative commons 2.5 licence please see
the website for details thanks to
Charlie Crowell and the Passaic Music
Network for the music used in the show
the song is called Vegas hard rock
travel
[Music]